American Association for Labor Legislation Records on Microfilm 5001 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Correspondence: 1934, Feb 12 - July 31. (Reel 51)
  During this period the questions of state vs. national social insurance and the endorsement of unemployment reserves on insurance were vigorously debated. I. M. Rubinow wrote John Andrews (4/13/34) in regard to unemployment insurance, and also said that he hoped they could affect a reconciliation. Andrews discussed budget problems in his correspondence with Eustace Seligman (4/18/34), AALL treasurer. The budget had been $72,000 in 1930. By 1933, it was down to $37,000 with a deficit of about $1,000. The lack of funds seriously curtailed the Associations work. Isador Lubin informed Andrews (5/22/34) about the President's quandry on the Wagner-Lewis bill and the President's plan to appoint a "royal commission" to report on needed social legislation. Edwin E. Witte wrote Andrews (6/19/34) that he found President Roosevelt's message on social insurance too vague, and that he might discourage state legislation on this issue. To Andrews' request to be appointed to the President's commission for the study of social insurance, Leo Wolman replied (6/26/34) that he would do anything he could to further the appointment.
- Correspondence: 1934, Aug 1 - 1935, Jan 24., 1934-1935 (Reel 52)
  The new United States Commission on Economic Security involved several active AALL members. Edwin E. Witte (8/1/34) and Arthur J. Altmeyer (8/17/34) wrote of their work and sought advice from Andrews. Frances Perkins, as chairman of the Commission, invited Andrews (10/30/34) to the White House Conference on Economic Security. In November (11/17/34), Andrews applied to the John and Mary Markle Foundation for a grant to cover the study of the extension of workmen's compensation to interstate commerce employees. A form letter sent out by the AALL (12/7/34) asked persons interested in seeing health insurance included in the new social insurance program to contact Frances Perkins immediately. Correspondence early in 1935 with the Railway Labor Executives Association (1/7/35), Edwin E. Witte (1/7/35) and Robert Wagner (1/11/35) concerns the bill drafted by Andrews and the AALL extending unemployment insurance to employees working in interstate commerce. Edwin E. Witte wrote (1/23/35) suggesting that Andrews testify for the economic security bill at the hearing.
- Correspondence: 1935, Jan 25 - Sept 30. (Reel 53)
  The economic security bill and workmen's compensation dominate the correspondence for this period. Edwin E. Witte thanked Andrews for his help with the economic security bill (2/23/35) but was worried that it would not be released from the House Ways and Means Committee. Witte asked if the AALL could stimulate some pressure. Andrews sent out an appropriate letter to the membership (2/25/35). Correspondence with members in southern states and with the general AALL membership concerning workmen's compensation continued. Andrews informed Paul Raushenbush (5/17/35) that Florida, South Carolina and North Carolina had all adopted workmen's compensation legislation in the first two weeks of May. The interstate commerce bill, as Andrews wrote to Senator Wagner (5/15/35), was in the process of being amended by an AALL committee. A long letter (8/11/35) gave Andrews Edwin E. Witte's reactions to the final passage of the Social Security Act, his own feelings toward it, toward Andrews and toward the work done by the AALL.
- Correspondence: 1935, Oct 1 - 1936, Mar 31., 1935-1936 (Reel 54)
  The launching of Social Security provoked much discussion. Edwin E. Witte reported (11/5/35) and Andrews "will certainly be considered," according to Altmeyer and Winant, for the Geneva appointment. (This probably refers to the position of American representative to the International Labor Office). Frances Perkins wrote to Andrews (1/3/36) to comment on his latest book, Administration of Labor Legislation. Edwin E. Witte wrote (1/25/36) that he felt that Abraham Epstein was trying to get credit for himself for the passage of the Social Security Sill and deny credit to President Roosevelt. The new year brought renewed interest in industrial safety. Walter Gellhorn, Frances Perkins, and several others corresponded with Andrews in February about problems concerning occupational disease, particularly silicosis and tuberculosis.
- Correspondence: 1936, April 1 - Dec 31. (Reel 55)
  In the spring a letter was sent out by the AALL (4/14/36), which was opposed to depriving silicosis victims of compensation. Andrews spent the summer in Europe, and in the fall tried to encourage new programs for the AALL. Isador Lubin invited Andrews (4/23/36) to be an adviser to the American delegation at the conference of the International Labor Office (ILO) in Geneva. Irene Andrews wrote Ethel Johnson, the ILO Washington representative (7/8/36), that after the Geneva meeting, John would be going back to England to complete his study of British factory inspection and labor law administration. When Andrews returned to New York, he reported to Edwin E. Witte (8/25/36) on the Geneva conference and the possibility of his spending another three months there in the fall. Andrews had been named a special agent to the United States Department of Labor and was asked to write a report on the results of his British factory inspection study. Andrews wrote Elizabeth Brandeis (10/5/36) that things were so difficult financially for the AALL that neither he nor Irene had drawn a salary for the last six months. Frances Perkins suggested to Andrews (11/24/36) that his proposed study of financing labor law administration be made under the sponsorship of the United States Bureau of Labor Statistics.
- Correspondence: 1937, Jan 1 - Oct 18. (Reel 56)
  Early in 1937, Andrews was appointed Acting Chief, Division of Legislative Aid, Bureau of Unemployment Compensation of the Social Security Board. During this period he sent out a form letter (3/8/37), seeking financial support for a study of the problem of silicosis and ventilation in state mine inspection. Fiorello LaGuardia invited Andrews (4/20/37) to join the panel of arbitrators of the New York City Industrial Relations Board. Andrews went to Europe in the summer. He wrote Professor Brainard that he would be attending the ILO conference and working at the ILO office in Geneva during June and July. On his return to the United States, he continued to work to raise mine safety standards. A letter from D. Harrington, Chief of the Health and Safety Branch of the United States Bureau of Mines (9/7/37), commented on changes Andrews suggested in state mine inspection policy.
- Correspondence: 1937, Oct 19 - 1939, Mar 31., 1937-1939 (Reel 57)
  During this period, the activity of the AALL continued to diminish, but a few new studies, such as those in the area of labor law administration, were undertaken. Andrews wrote E. W. Bakke (1/3/38) about the AALL study of municipal labor legislation. The budget reached a new low of $25,000. Andrews suggested (1/29/38) to the treasurer, Eustace Seligman, that a special effort be made to secure funds for mine safety, physical examinations for workers, and the ratification of the ILO maritime conventions. John Andrews sent John Winant at the ILO, Geneva (5/6/38), parts of the report on labor inspection in the United States. Andrews returned to Geneva that summer. Andrews and Walter Gellhorn corresponded through October and December on the "...baby Wagner Act" and the Walsh-Healy Bill that the AALL was setting up for the Rhode Island Federation of Labor. Andrews sent the Walsh-Healy Bill to the Rhode Island Federation of Labor (12/22/38). During the first three months of 1939, amendments to the interstate workmen's compensation bill were prepared. Andrews sent Robert Wagner (1/22/39) amendments to the interstate workmen's bill which he hoped Wagner would approve and reintroduce. Frances Perkins replied (1/27/39) to Andrews' note in regard to the Harry Bridges case: "It helps a great deal to hear from one's.. ." John A. Kratz (2/24/39) gave Andrews credit for the original passage of the Vocational Rehabilitation Act and thanked Andrews for his suggestions. Andrews also wrote to Harold Ickes (2/25/39) and (3/1/39), making suggestions for improved administration of vocational rehabilitation.
- Correspondence: 1939, Mar 21 - 1940, May 18., 1939-1940 (Reel 58)
  Mine safety was a key issue in late 1939 and the beginning of 1940. D. Harrington contacted Andrews about the disaster at the Duvin mine near Providence, Kentucky. Edwin E. Witte wrote Andrews (8/29/39) and Andrews replied (9/18/39) about revisions that Arthur J. Altmeyer forced Witte to make in an article. Andrews thought the changes were ridiculous. John L. Lewis complimented Andrews (2/10/40) on the letter the AALL distributed on the need for mine safety legislation, and asked Andrews to remove his name from the Association letterhead, as his policy did not permit his name to be used. The Director of the Department of Engineering of the United Mine Workers, Walter Polakov, also wrote, agreeing to cooperate with the AALL on improving mine safety regulations (2/20/40). Sidney Hillman wrote to John Andrews (4/1/40) about possible multi-shift regulations.
- Correspondence: 1940, May 19 - 1941, May 31., 1940-1941 (Reel 59)
  John Andrews wrote to the President (11/8/40), suggesting that Roosevelt's legislative program include completion of the health program by supporting social security protection, authorization of federal mine safety inspection, and the extension of workmen's compensation to all interstate employees. This was largely the AALL's program for 1941. Harold Ickes, Secretary of the Interior, wrote to Andrews (2/25/41) about federal mine inspection. The AALL sent a form letter (3/25/41) to the state departments of labor, asking about the failure of employers to insure their employees. In April, Andrews wrote to Merritt L. Gordon (4/14/41), relating the early years of the AALL. Andrews stated that he had attended the first organizational meeting in December 1905. Arthur J. Altmeyer wrote about the need for physical examinations for workers (5/8/41). Andrews outlined the new aims of the AALL in a letter to Professor H. Pillsbury Styles (5/8/41). He stressed federal health and disability insurance and the adoption of the federal mine inspection bill.
- Correspondence: 1941, June 1 - 1945, Dec 31, n.d., fragments., 1941-1945 (Reel 60)
  Andrews wrote Morris Leeds and others (1/15/42) of his interest in regularizing the textile industry and stopping its practice of running three shifts for some weeks and then shutting down in others, The threat of the second world war was felt. Andrews cautioned the membership "to be watchful lest (by) their short-sighted good intention many of our labor laws be broken down" (2/1/42). Andrews complained to C. Edwin Gilmore (2/2/42) that "We are in a tidal sweep of federalization in the field of labor legislation." Plans for the annual meeting were discussed with Professor C. Clively in October (10/8/42), which suggested a joint meeting with the Rural Sociological Society on Mexican workers in the United States and the general need for extending social security protection to farm workers. One of Andrews' last letters in the collection, written shortly before his death, is to Barbara Peterson of the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, explaining that for the first time the AALL's annual meeting would be cancelled ".. .on account of wartime conditions."
- Organizational Materials, 1906-1942; 1 (Reel 61)
  and no date
- General Labor Law, 1909-1919; 2 (Reel 61)
- General Labor Law, 1920-1943; 1 (Reel 62)
- General Social Insurance, 1909-1937; 2 (Reel 62)
- Health Insurance, 1911-1917; 3 (Reel 62)
- Health Insurance, 1917-1940 (Reel 63)
  and no date. Also includes fragments
- Industrial Safety, Diseases and Accidents, 1909-1942 (Reel 64)
- Labor Law Administration, 1912-1940; 1 (Reel 65)
- Factory Inspection Studies, 1928-1940; 2 (Reel 65)
- Old Age Pension and Insurance, 1910-1928; 3 (Reel 65)
- Old Age Pension and Insurance, 1929-1940; 1 (Reel 66)
- Unemployment, 1909-1932; 2 (Reel 66)
- Unemployment, 1933-1942; 1 (Reel 67)
- Wages, Hours and Conditions, 1910-1924; 2 (Reel 67)
- Wages, Hours and Conditions, 1925-1942; 1 (Reel 68)
- Workmen's Compensation, 1906-1924; 2 (Reel 68)
- Workmen's Compensation, 1924-1942; 1 (Reel 69)
- Miscellaneous, 1915-1940; 2 (Reel 69)
- Unionism, 1906-1940; 1 (Reel 70)
- Pamphlets, 1910-1942; 2 (Reel 70)
- Broadsides, 1909-1940; 3 (Reel 70)
- Press Releases, 1910-1917; 4 (Reel 70)
  1910 - September, 1917
- Press Releases, 1917-1940 (Reel 71)
  October, 1917 - 1940, and no date.